｢There was a hungry crow｣
♪ ｢お 腹 空 かせた ｶﾗｽがいた｣
｢Who wanted to get some feed｣
♪ ｢なんとか 餌 に ありつきたい｣
｢If only this beak were a little longer｣
♪ ｢この くちばしが もっと長ければ｣
｢That feed would be a bit closer｣
♪ ｢あの餌が もっと こっちに来れば｣
♪ ～
♪ ～
｢A crow can think｣
｢ｶﾗｽは考える ｶﾗｽは考える ｶﾗｽは考える ｶﾗｽは考える｣
｢can think... can think｣
♪ ｢考える 考える｣
Observe, then propose a hypothesis, experiment and consider results.
( 斎藤 )観察し 仮 説を立て 実験をし 考察する｡
Lean the way of scientific thought.
科学の考え方を学べ｡
We begin with a thinking observation.
(山本)まずは ｢考える観察｣から｡
When we look at the water in a bathtub...
おふろに たまっている 水を 見ると →
We can see it has some color.
色が ついているように 見える｡
It's greenish blue.
緑がかった 青色だ｡
But water ought to be transparent. Why can we see a color?
水は とうめいな はずなのに なぜ 色がついて 見えるのか？
Perhaps it's because we're looking at it in the bath.
おふろ場で 見ているせいかもしれない｡
Filling a glass. let's try looking outside the bath.
ｺｯﾌﾟに くんで 外で 見てみる｡
There's no color. It's clear.
色は 無い｡ とうめいだ｡
To make sure let's compare to an empty glass.
念のため 空のｺｯﾌﾟと くらべてみる｡
The one with water has a little more color but
水が 入っているほうが ほんの少し 青い気もするが →
it's hard to tell.
はっきりとは わからない｡
What will happen if we increase the number of glasses?
では ｺｯﾌﾟを重ねていけば どうなるか？
The light color has increased, and we can see blue can't we.
うすい色が 重なって 青が 見えてくるのではないか？
We can see blue.
青い色が 見えてきた｡
But the water's color isn't significant.
でも これ 水の色が 重なって こくなったんじゃなくて →
Perhaps it's the color of the glass which makes the color visible.
ｶﾞﾗｽの色が 重なって 青く 見えているのかもしれない｡
We prepare a long tube.
長い つつを 用意した｡
Both ends are closed.
両わきは とじてある｡
We fill it with water via a hole on top.
上に 開けた 穴 から 水を 入れていく｡
It's full.
水が いっぱいになった｡
When we look from the side it appears transparent.
横から見ると とうめいだが →
But when we look lengthwise...
たてに 見ると…｡
it's blue.
青い｡
It's quite similar to the color in the bath.
おふろの色に かなり にている｡
So is the water blue because of its depth?
やはり 水は おくゆきがあると 青く 見えるのか？
Let's try comparig it to the bath water.
おふろと くらべてみる｡
It's appears to be the same color but the blue in the bath water is a little deeper.
同じような色だが 少し おふろのほうが 色が こい｡
Is it because there's more water there?
水が 多いからなのか？
Let's try pulling the plug.
せんを ぬいてみる｡
What will happen to the color?
色の こさは どうなるのか？
♪ ～
♪ ～
(口笛)
(口笛)
♪ ～
♪ ～
Today's experiment
( 蒼井 )今日は この… →
uses a clear super-ball.
よく はずむ とうめいな ﾎﾞｰﾙを使った実験です｡
We put the ball into a round glass of water.
この ﾎﾞｰﾙを 水の入った 丸いビンに入れます｡
If we do this what will happen?
すると どうなるか？
It looks much bigger.
大きく 見えます｡
The glass is acting like a lens.
ビンが ﾚﾝｽﾞのような 役目をしているんですね｡
Now, this time...
そして 今度は このﾎﾞｰﾙに…｡
we put a small sticker on the ball.
小さな ｼｰﾙを はります｡
When we look at this from behind...
これを うらから 見ると…｡
It looks big.
やはり 大きく見えます｡
Now this is the problem.
さて ここからが 問題です｡
We put the ball in the water like this.
この ﾎﾞｰﾙを このまま 水の中に 入れます｡
If we do the way we see the sticker
すると ｼｰﾙの見え方は →
How will it change?
この時と くらべて どう 変化するでしょうか？
Well then let's try it.
では やってみましょう｡
We'll present the answer at the end of the program.
答えは 番組の最後で 発表します｡
Everyone, think about it very hard, won't you?
みなさん よ～く 考えておいてくださいね｡
♪ ～
♪ ～
では 先ほどの答えです｡ And now the answer from earlier.
では 先ほどの答えです｡
Everyone did you think about it carefully?
みなさん ちゃんと 考えましたか？
Now, let's try it for real.
では 実さいに やってみましょう｡ いきますよ｡
What will happen, please look carefully, won't you?
どうなるか よ～く 見ていてくださいね｡
Did you get it? The answer is...
わかりました？ 答えは…
Even though the ball looks bigger...
ﾎﾞｰﾙ そのものは 大きく見えるのに →
the sticker looks smaller.
ｼｰﾙは 小さく見える｡
Why do you think that is?
どうして そうなるのでしょう？
Well at first the sticker looked big because the light was bent.
そもそも ｼｰﾙが 大きく見えるのは 光が 曲がるからです｡
Light has a property so that when it travels between different materials...
光は ある 物質 から 別の物質に 進む時 →
At that boundary the light is bent.
その さかい目で 曲がる事があります｡
And the ball in the water...
ﾎﾞｰﾙを 水に…｡
From here on we think for ourselves.
ここから先は 自分で考えよう｡
From here on everyone is a thinking crow.
これからは みんなが｢考えるｶﾗｽ｣｡